A Guide to the National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 2, Accession 2 FA1184
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 2, Accession 2
1966-2010
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations, Inc.
FA1184
18.47 Cubic Feet 41.5 document boxes, 1 oversized flat box, 1 records storage box
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The National Committee on United States-China Relations donated its records to the Rockefeller Archive Center by deed of gift dated March 27, 2015.
Biographical / Historical
The National Committee on United States – China Relations (NCUSCR) was established in 1966 as a nonprofit educational organization with a mission to encourage mutual understanding and dialogue between citizens of the United States and China.
The National Committee came into being through the cooperative efforts of scholars and civic, religious, and business leaders who, at a time of mutual hostility between the two countries, sought to stimulate public discussion about China and the United States' relations with it by sponsoring conferences, seminars, publications, and other education and outreach programs. In 1972, the National Committee sponsored the Chinese table tennis team's historic U. S. visit. This round of "Ping Pong Diplomacy," which followed closely on Richard Nixon's visit to China in February 1972, helped pave the way for later exchanges and, eventually, for the normalization of relations with China in 1979. Building on these cultural exchanges, the National Committee came to be a primary organizer of professional and policy exchanges between the two countries (and including Hong Kong and Taiwan), in the areas of foreign affairs and international relations, economic development, governance and legal affairs, education, mass media, environmental and global issues, etc. As its role in exchanges became more prominent, the National Committee turned over some of its educational programs to the Asia Society in the late 1970s, but it continues its educational role through public education events and ongoing outreach.
Funding for the National Committee comes from the United States government (especially the Department of State), corporations, and foundations, as well as from its individual membership.
Scope and Contents
RG 2 of the NCUSCR records contains files documenting its sponsorship of Conferences, Seminars, Workshops, and Dialogues on foreign policy and relations with China, including U. S. - China Dialogues, which ran from 1984 to 2002. Files in the Programs, Projects, and Proposals series concern the U.S. - China Labor Law Cooperation project, 2002-2007, and the National Committee's University Field Staff program, 1966-1973. RG 2 also contains records of Exchanges to China through the Fulbright-Hays Summer Seminars Abroad, for the period 1982-2010, as well as a few general Exchanges files. A series of Personnel files is restricted.
Arrangement
The records of the National Committee on United States – China Relations are divided into ten record groups, which reflect the order in which the records were received (but which are otherwise an artificial distinction). The records are sorted intellectually into series, which carry over through all record groups, but they have received little or no physical rearrangement. RG 2 of the NCUSCR records contains records from five series: 2 - Exchanges - General; 3 - Exchanges to China; 5 - Conferences, Seminars, Workshops, and Dialogues; 8 - Programs, Projects, and Proposals; 17 - Personnel records.
- Events, 1995; 1
  - NCUSCR Gala Dinner (Waldorf-Astoria), Tapes 1-2, 1995 September 18; FA1184:030; Audio: 2 Cassette Tapes.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copy currently unavailable. See a RAC archivist for further assistance.
    Scope and Contents
    Two cassette tapes described as a pair. Gala Dinner identification based on date and location information written on tapes.
    Related Materials
    See Gala Dinner file in RG 1, FA772, Box 120, Folder 1676.
- Exchanges - General, 1986-2000; 2
  The Exchanges - General series in RG 2 is a small set of files that documents agreements between the National Committee and the U. S. Department of Education concerning the administration of Fulbright exchange programs with China. It also includes materials relating to conference presentations on the Fulbright teacher exchange experience.
  - NCUSCR Subcommittee on Education and Communications, 1986-1987 (Box 31, Folder 269)
  - North American Social Studies Conference: Teaching about China - The Fulbright Experience, 1992 November (Box 33, Folder 291)
    Presentation at the National Council for the Social Studies annual meeting by participants in the 1991 and 1992 Fulbright summer seminars to China.
  - FA1184:013 - North American Social Studies Conference: Teaching about China - The Fulbright Experience, 1992 November; Still Image: 1 3x5 color snapshot. (Box 42, Folder 291)
    Image of Chinese villagers smiling over a Polaroid photograph. Enclosed in Donna Genet to Elizabeth Knup, February 17, 1992.
  - National Council for the Social Studies Conference: Teaching about China - The Fulbright Experience, 1996 November (Box 35, Folder 305)
    Workshop with participants in the 1995 Fulbright summer seminar to China. File includes unidentified photo of workshop participants.
  - U. S. Department of Education, 1995-1996 (Box 35, Folder 306)
    Correspondence concerning administration and budgeting for Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad programs and reciprocal Education delegations from China.
  - U. S. Department of Education, 1997-1998 (Box 36, Folder 314)
  - U. S. Department of Education, 1998-1999 (Box 36, Folder 321)
    Correspondence concerning National Committee role in Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad programs and reciprocal Education delegations from China.
  - U. S. Department of Education (Business Proposal), 2000 (Box 37, Folder 322)
    Solicitation Number: RFP-ED-00-R-0002. NCUSCR Proposal for operation of Fulbright-Hays Summer Seminars in China and Chinese Educators delegations, 2001-2005.
- Exchanges to China, 1977-2010; 3
  The Exchanges to China series in RG 2 documents Fulbright-Hays Seminars to China from 1982 to 2010. This program, which the National Committee ran for the U. S. Department of Education and the Chinese Ministry of Education, sent sixteen American teachers (and sometimes post-secondary educators) to China each summer on a five-week study tour of Chinese history and culture, or in a few cases language training. Files include namelists, itineraries, reports, detailed program evaluations by the participants, and some of the curriculum projects that teachers created upon their return. In addition to the Fulbright seminars, the series also includes records of delegations of local and state education leaders who visited China in 1977 and 1978.
  - State Education Leaders Delegation: China's Schools in Flux (1978), 1977 October 28 - November 15 (Box 29, Folder 254)
    Manuscript report dated 1978 September 25. Manuscript not complete. Several papers were loosely inserted in the bound file.
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation: China's Schools Report Manuscript, 1978 June 22 - July 8 (Box 29, Folder 255)
    Correspondence, outlines, and captions, relating to manuscript of "Children's Palaces: Education in the People's Republic of China as Photographed and Interpreted by American Educators."
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation: Report (Draft Pages), 1978 June 22 - July 8 (Box 29, Folder 256)
    Original folder marked Draft 2, File 1. Presumably relates to photo essay "Children's Palaces: Education in the People's Republic of China as Photographed and Interpreted by American Educators." File consists of individual manuscript pages with attached photos. Includes the illustrated "Ballad of Leadership Local," by Lawrence Cremin.
  - Local Education Leaders Delegation: Report (Draft Pages), 1978 June 22 - July 8; FA1184:011; Still Image: 8 3.5 x 5 color snapshots. (Box 42, Folder 256)
    Images of Chinese schools and schoolchildren. Unmounted photos interfiled among manuscript pages.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China - Evaluation, 1980 (Box 29, Folder 257)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar on Chinese History and Culture, 1982 (Box 29, Folder 258)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar on Chinese History and Culture, 1982 (Box 30, Folder 259)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar on Chinese History and Culture, 1983 (Box 30, Folder 260)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar on Chinese History and Culture, 1983 (Box 30, Folder 260A)
    Restricted - confidential material.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar on Chinese History and Culture, 1984 (Box 30, Folder 261)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar on Chinese History and Culture, 1985 (Box 30, Folder 262)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar on Chinese History and Culture, 1986 (Box 30, Folder 263)
  - Community College Presidents Delegation, Fulbright Summer Seminar on the Chinese Education System and Reform, 1986 June 11 - July 4 (Box 30, Folder 264)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminars to China: Curriculum Projects and Debriefing, 1985-1986 (Box 30, Folder 265)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminars to China: Curriculum Projects and Debriefing, 1985-1986; FA1184:012; Still Image: 4 color 5x7 prints. (Box 42, Folder 265)
    Photos of furnished rooms in Chinese apartment or dormitory. Connection to other materials in file unknown.
  - University Faculty Delegation, Fulbright Summer Seminar on Contemporary China, 1987 June 1 - July 2 (Box 30, Folder 266)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar on Chinese History and Culture: General, 1987 June 14 - July 18 (Box 30, Folder 267)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar on Chinese History and Culture: Curriculum Projects, 1987 (Box 30, Folder 268)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar on Chinese History and Culture: General, 1988 (Box 31, Folder 270)
    The 1988 Fulbright delegation was the first to combine the program for high-school and university level teachers.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar on Chinese History and Culture: Evaluations, 1988 (Box 31, Folder 271)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminars to China (Postponed), 1989 (Box 31, Folder 272)
  - Fulbright Scholars Orientation Program, 1989 (Box 31, Folder 273 - 274)
    For 1989-1990 academic year. In the wake of the Tiananmen Square protests, the Fulbright program in China was postponed, and scholars were posted to other countries in Asia.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminars to China: General, 1990 (Box 31, Folder 275)
    Seminars on "China: Tradition and Transformation" and "China's Economic Development."
  - Fulbright Summer Seminars to China: General, 1990; FA1184:045; Digital Media: 5.5" floppy disk.
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy is currently available. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
    (Fulbright Proposal, 1990). Disk variously labeled "Rotary talk, USIA, FY 1990"; AEI Singapore letters Sullivan, Spencer?." Identification comes from an accompanying note.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminars to China: Materials sent to participants, 1990 (Box 31, Folder 276)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminars to China: Evaluations, 1990 (Box 31, Folder 277)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminars to China: Trip Reports, 1990 (Box 32, Folder 278)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminars to China: Thank Yous and Follow-Up, 1990 (Box 32, Folder 279)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to Taiwan (IIE), 1990 June 3 - July 7 (Box 32, Folder 280)
    Seminar on China's Arts in Transition, administered by the Institute of International Education.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 1991 (Box 32, Folder 281)
    Trip also included visits to Hong Kong and Taiwan. Background and Planning, Briefing,
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar: Hong Kong and Taiwan, 1991 (Box 32, Folder 282)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Report, Itinerary, Namelist, 1991 (Box 32, Folder 283)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations, 1991 (Box 32, Folder 284)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Follow-Up, Projects, and Accomplishments, 1991 (Box 32, Folder 285)
    File includes photo (not separated) of Beth Dutton receiving Outstanding Vermont Teacher award, October 16, 1991.
  - Fulbright Scholars Orientation Program, 1991 (Box 32, Folder 286)
    Proposal to USIA for briefing for full-year exchange program.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 1992 (Box 32, Folder 287)
    Correspondence with the PRC, Hong Kong, and Taiwan
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 1992 (Box 33, Folder 288)
    Background and Planning; Briefing and Materials sent to Participants.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Report, Itinerary, Namelist, 1992 (Box 33, Folder 289)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations, 1992 (Box 33, Folder 290)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 1993 (Box 33, Folder 292)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Report and Itinerary, 1993 (Box 33, Folder 293)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1993 (Box 33, Folder 294)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 1994 (Box 33, Folder 295)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Trip Report and Itinerary, 1994 (Box 34, Folder 296)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1994 (Box 34, Folder 297-298)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1994; FA1184:014; Still Image: 1 color 4x6 snapshot. (Box 42, Folder 297)
    Group photo of the Crew at Tiananmen Sqare.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1994; FA1184:015; Still Image: 2 color3x5 snapshots. (Box 42, Folder 297)
    2 group photos of delegation in China
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1994; FA1184:016; Still Image: 7 color 4x6 snapshots. (Box 42, Folder 297)
    7 images of schoolchildren working on Chinese culture projects at Sunnybrae School and Wilson School, Trenton, NJ.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1994; FA1184:017; Still Image: 1 color 4x6 snapshot. (Box 42, Folder 298)
    Photo of delegates at a "25-variety dumpling dinner." Captioned "A little Xian action." Sent by Patricia Flores.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 1995 (Box 34, Folder 299)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 1995; FA1184:046; Digital Media: 1 3.5" floppy disk
    Fulbright Briefing Book, 1995
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Trip Report and Itinerary, 1995 (Box 34, Folder 300)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1995 (Box 34, Folder 301)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1995; FA1184:018; Still image: 1 4x6 color snapshot (Box 42, Folder 301)
    Participant Barbara Spillane, standing next to library display on China
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 1996 (Box 34, Folder 302)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Trip Report and Itinerary, 1996 (Box 34, Folder 303)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1996 (Box 35, Folder 304)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1996; FA1184:019; Still Image: 11 color snapshots (3x5) (Box 42, Folder 304)
    Views of Harbour View hotel, Hong Kong; participant receiving massage; Pudong, Shanghia; restaurant tank with frogs and snakes
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 1997 (Box 35, Folder 307)
    File inludes passport-size photos of participants.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Trip Report and Itinerary, 1997 (Box 35, Folder 308)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1997 (Box 35, Folder 309)
    Includes snapshot (not separated) of toast at Pre-Trip Briefing dinner, sent by Anita Linn.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 1998 (Box 35, Folder 310)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Trip Report and Itinerary, 1998 (Box 35, Folder 311)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Curriculum Projects, 1998 (Box 35, Folder 312)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1998 (Box 36, Folder 313)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminars to China: Curriculum Projects, 1984-1997; Microfiche: Retained in file. (Box 36, Folder 315)
    ERIC (Clearinghouse for Social Studies/Social Science Education) editions on microfiche of Fulbright curriculum projects for 1984, 1992, 1993, 1996, and 1997. File also includes lists of curriculum projects for 1984-1988.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 1999 (Box 36, Folder 316-317)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Trip Report and Itinerary, 1999 (Box 36, Folder 318)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Curriculum Projects, 1999 (Box 36, Folder 319)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Curriculum Projects, 1999; FA1184:047; Digital Media: 3.5" floppy disk.
    Marianne Kenney, Curriculum Project: 1) Rural to Urban Migration, 2) Voyage of Thought, 3) Three Gorges Dam.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Curriculum Projects, 1999; FA1184:020; Still Image: 17 4x6 color snapshots. (Box 42, Folder 319)
    Shirley Bell's classroom activities and displays on China. Captions on back of images.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1999 (Box 36, Folder 320)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations and Follow-Up, 1999; FA1184:021; Still Image: 7 color slides (Box 42, Folder 319)
    Labeled slides of delegation trip, by Elizabeth J. Miller, enclosed with her Evaluation.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China:General, 2000 (Box 37, Folder 323)
    Includes passport-size photos of delegates (not separated).
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Hong Kong and PRC, 2000 (Box 37, Folder 324)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Trip Report and Itinerary, 2000 (Box 37, Folder 325)
    Includes correspondence with scholar escort Craig Canning.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluation and Follow Up, 2000 (Box 37, Folder 326)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluation and Follow Up, 2000 (Box 37, Folder 326A)
    Restricted - confidential material - Open in 2031.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluation and Follow Up, 2000; FA1184:022; Still Image: 1 color 4x6 print (Box 42, Folder 326)
    Snapshot of Chinese children and their mothers, entitled "Our Gang Chinese style."
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluation and Follow Up, 2000; FA1184:023; Still Image: 43 color prints (4 x 7 - 4 x 11.5 panoramic prints) (Box 42, Folder 326)
    Photos from Pre-departure Briefing and trip. No identifications given. A few images appear to be of a Chinese delegation in the U.S.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 2001 (Box 37, Folder 327)
    Background and Planning, PRC and Hong Kong, Pre-departure Briefing, Scholar Escort Stanley Rosen.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Correspondence with Participants, 2001 (Box 37, Folder 328)
    Includes passport-size photos of participants.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Trip Report and Itinerary, 2001 (Box 37, Folder 329)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations, 2001 (Box 37, Folder 330)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Thank Yous and Follow-Up, 2001 (Box 38, Folder 331)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Thank Yous and Follow-Up, 2001; FA1184:024; Still Image: 6 color 4x6 prints (Box 42, Folder 331)
    Area Studies students at Gung Hee Fat Choy Party, Sacred Heart Academy, Honolulu. Sent by Claire McCaffery Griffin, February 14, 2002.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Thank Yous and Follow-Up, 2001; FA1184:025; Still Image: 3 4x6 color images printed on one 8.5 x 11 photo sheet. (Box 42, Folder 331)
    Images of delegates Dana Lynch and David Bilka with Chinese family and students. Photos and captions sent by Dana Lynch, 2001.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 2002 (Box 38, Folder 332)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 2002; FA1184:048; Digital Media: 1 CD-R
    Fulbright-Hayes China 2002, from Rick Belsky (contents not known).
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 2002; FA1184:049; Digital Media: 1 CD-R
    James Kerr, Fulbright China Program Pictures, July 2002
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Correspondence and Planning (PRC and Hong Kong), 2002 (Box 38, Folder 333)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Trip Report, Itinerary, and Follow-Up, 2002 (Box 38, Folder 334)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations, 2002 (Box 38, Folder 335)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Evaluations, 2002 (Box 38, Folder 335A)
    Restricted - confidential material - Open in 2033.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China (2003 group): General, 2004 (Box 38, Folder 336)
    The 2003 delegation did not travel to China until 2004, because of the SARS epidemic. File includes Trip Report and Itinerary.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China (2003 group): Evaluations and Follow-Up, 2004 (Box 38, Folder 337)
    The 2003 delegation did not travel to China until 2004, because of the SARS epidemic. File includes two curriculum projects.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China (2003 group): Evaluations and Follow-Up, 2004; FA1184:050; Digital Media: 1 CD.
    Kathleen T. Gates Curriculum Project (powerpoint).
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China (2003 and 2004 groups) (Box 38, Folder 338)
    Participant information and Pre-Departure Briefing.`
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 2004 (Box 38, Folder 339)
    Includes Evaluations, Report, and Itinerary.
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Curriculum Projects, 2004 (Box 38, Folder 340)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: General, 2005 (Box 38, Folder 341)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Trip Report and Evaluations, 2005 (Box 39, Folder 342)
  - Fulbright Summer Seminar to China: Trip Report and Evaluations, 2005 (Box 39, Folder 342A)
    Restricted - confidential material - Open in 2036.
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Applications, 2006 (Box 39, Folder 343)
    File includes passport-size photos of delegates (not separated).
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Evaluations, 2006 (Box 39, Folder 344)
  - Fulbright-Hays Seminars Abroad: Thank Yous, 2006 (Box 39, Folder 345)
  - Fulbright- Hays Seminars Abroad: History and Culture - General, 2007 (Box 39, Folder 346)
  - Fulbright- Hays Seminars Abroad: History and Culture - Applications, 2007 (Box 39, Folder 347)
  - Fulbright- Hays Seminars Abroad: History and Culture - Evaluations and Report, 2007 (Box 39, Folder 348)
  - Fulbright- Hays Seminars Abroad: Language Training -General, 2007 (Box 39, Folder 349)
    Native and Foreign Language Instruction and Training seminar group. File includes passport-size photos of delegates (not separated).
  - Fulbright- Hays Seminars Abroad: Language Training - Applications, 2007 (Box 40, Folder 350)
    Native and Foreign Language Instruction and Training seminar group.
  - Fulbright- Hays Seminars Abroad: Language Training - Evaluations and Reports, 2007 (Box 40, Folder 351)